A Guide to the Laurance S. Rockefeller papers, Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, RG 2 FA433
Rockefeller Archive Center
Laurance S. Rockefeller papers, Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, RG 2
1878-1972
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
FA433
25.29 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
Laurance Spelman Rockefeller was born on May 26, 1910, in New York City, the fourth of the six children of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He attended Lincoln School, a progressive coeducational preparatory school connected with Teachers College of Columbia University in New York City, before entering Princeton in 1928. A philosophy major, he graduated from Princeton in 1932 with a B.A. degree in philosophy and went on to two years of graduate study at Harvard Law School.
On August 15, 1934, Laurance Rockefeller married Mary French in the Congregational Church in Woodstock, Vermont. Together they raised three daughters and a son.
During World War II, Laurance Rockefeller served in the Navy (1942-1945), attaining the rank of lieutenant commander.
Laurance Rockefeller pursued a number of successful careers during his lifetime. He was a pioneer in the field of venture capital. He was a leading and influential figure for three decades in the American conservation movement. He led the development of one of the world's foremost cancer care and research facilities, and was both a benefactor and advisor to major educational institutions. And, with great foresight, he combined his personal vision for conservation, recreation, and the spiritual needs of individuals to develop internationally acclaimed environmentally oriented resorts. His many accomplishments have been recognized both nationally and internationally.
In 1935, he began working in the family office in Rockefeller Center. His first duties were to develop his knowledge and understanding of Rockefeller philanthropic activities, conservation projects, and business interests, through both study and playing a modest role in their operation. Simultaneously, he developed his own special interest, blending business acumen with the talents of a "gadgeteer," a label he once pinned on himself.
He became well known as an investor of risk capital in young enterprises whose future was based primarily on scientific and technological developments. Over the years his investment interests included the fields of aviation, aerospace, electronics, high temperature physics, composite materials, optics, lasers, data processing, thermionics, instrumentation, and nuclear power. Beginning in August 1969, his venture capital investments in these areas were made through a venture capital group, Venrock, formed by members of the Rockefeller family.
In a different area of venture capital, he developed outstanding environmentally oriented resort hotels in Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Hawaii, and Vermont, serving as chairman of Rockresorts, Inc., a resort management company which he founded and chaired.
Conservation of the environment and recreational development constituted much of Laurance Rockefeller's philanthropy and public service. His introduction to public service came in 1939 when Governor Herbert H. Lehman of New York appointed him to the Palisades Interstate Park Commission (PIPC). He was president of the PIPC from 1970 to 1977 and continued as a commissioner until his resignation in December 1978. He was an advisor to Presidents Eisenhower, Kennedy, Johnson, Nixon, and Ford on matters of environmental conservation and outdoor recreation, and he worked on federal commissions set up to help develop national conservation and environmental policies and programs. In 1958, President Dwight D. Eisenhower appointed him chairman of the Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission (ORRRC), which charted ways of meeting the nation's outdoor recreation needs through the year 2000. He was a special emissary for President Lyndon Johnson in the effort that led to creation of the National Redwoods Park in California, and he served as chairman of President Nixon's Citizens' Advisory Committee on Environmental Quality, successor to a similar group which he headed under President Johnson. He played a pivotal role in the creation and development of several national parks including Grand Teton National Park in Wyoming, Virgin Islands National Park on the island of St. John, and Marsh-Billings-Rockefeller National Historical Park in Vermont.
He served as a leader of several important nonprofit and philanthropic organizations. He was president and later chairman of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1958-1980) and was a trustee of the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation (1960-1982). His first association with Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center in New York City was in 1947; he also served as chairman (1960-1982), overseeing an expansion and modernization of its operations. He was a longtime trustee of the New York Zoological Society (1935-1986) and served as its president (1969-1971) and chairman (1971-1985).
Laurance Rockefeller received many honors for his efforts on behalf of the environment and cancer research and treatment. Among them are the Alfred P. Sloan, Jr. Memorial Award from the American Cancer Society (1969), the Medal of Freedom (1969), Commander (Honorary) of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (1971), the Woodrow Wilson Award from Princeton University (1991), the Congressional Gold Medal (1991), the Chairman's Award from the National Geographic Society (1995), the Theodore Roosevelt National Park Medal of Honor (1995), and the Lady Bird Johnson Conservation Award for Lifetime Achievement (1997). In 2003, he became the first person to be made an honorary citizen of the British Virgin Islands in recognition of his many contributions to the area. In December 1959 he received the National Institute of Social Sciences' Gold Medal for distinguished services to humanity, an award previously bestowed upon his grandfather and father. This was the first time in the Institute's history that three generations of a family had been so honored. The citation to Laurance Rockefeller proclaimed him as a "creative organizer of ventures into new fields of human endeavor for the growing aspirations of mankind; [and a] leader in the conservation of natural resources and in the development of the medical and social sciences for the welfare of the individual." In 1967, the National Institute awarded Gold Medals to all five Rockefeller brothers in recognition of their individual and collective services to humanity.
Laurance Rockefeller died on July 11, 2004, at his home in Manhattan.
Prepared by Rockefeller Family and Associates, June 1982, and 2004.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted. Access is subject to the restrictions specified in the original deed of gift of November 13, 1986, and in the subsequent 2009 deed of gift by LSR's executors.
Material in the Rockefeller family collections which provides the names, correspondence or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net worth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Laurance S. Rockefeller papers include:
FA434 Laurance S. Rockefeller papers, Speech Files, RG 5
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into seven series:
1. Correspondence
2. Personal Papers
3. Business Interests
4. Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center
5. Financial Materials
6. Laurance S. Rockefeller Family
7. Audiovisual materials
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: correspondence, personal material, and audiovisual material.
- Office of the Messieurs Rockefeller (OMR) Files, 1878-1972; bulk; 2; 21 Cubic Feet
  Related Archival Materials note
  LSR's personal and business interests and activities are more fully documented in subject files in the Rockefeller Family Archives, Office of the Messieurs Rockefeller (OMR) records, in, for example, Business Interests, Cultural Interests, and other series.
  Later files that formed part of LSR's 1986 deed of gift were not included in RG 2 of the LSR Papers. They will be processed along with later series of LSR papers of a corresponding date range.
  Appraisal note
  Duplicate copies of reports, circulars, or correspondence in a file were discarded.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Received from Laurance S. Rockefeller by deed of gift, November 13, 1986, and through subsequent additions.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in 7 series: 1. Correspondence; 2. Personal Papers; 3. Business Interests; 4. Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center; 5. Financial Materials; 6. Laurance S. Rockefeller Family and Series 7: Audiovisual materials.
  The OMR Files materials were initially arranged by Dr. Joseph W. Ernst, the Rockefeller family archivist, and a copy of his finding aid is included in the Appendix. The present arrangement preserves the original folder titles as far as is practicable.
  Within series, folders are arranged alphabetically by title. Arrangement within files is generally chronological, though occasionally an alphabetical series of documents will follow the chronological series. The family office normally sorted documents in reverse chronological order. We have generally undone this reverse order and have arranged records within a folder from the earliest date to the latest. The family office also commonly created smaller groupings of records (around a topic or individual) within a general chronological file. These groupings consequently form sorts of chronological (and subject) balloons within the regular order of the file. Documents within a grouping may span several years, but the date of the last item determines the placement of the documents within the file. In some cases we have used paper folders or inserted blank sheets of paper to mark the interruptions or distinctions.
  Other Finding Aids note
  Dr. Joseph W. Ernst initially arranged the OMR files that make up this record group, and a copy of his finding aid is available at the Rockefeller Archive Center. The present arrangement preserves the original folder titles as far as is practicable.
  The Rockefeller Archive Center has microfilm of a card index of names and subjects that the Rockefeller family office general files department created and maintained for the records transferred to the department. It employed a numeric system and descriptive titles to mark up and index the records. While the card entries are not exhaustive, they provide item level access to many of the documents. Access copies of the microfilm are available at the RAC.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted. Access is subject to the restrictions specified in the original deed of gift of November 13, 1986, and in the subsequent 2009 deed of gift by LSR's executors.
  Material in the Rockefeller family collections which provides the names, correspondence or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net worth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
  Personal financial materials relating to Laurance S. Rockefeller and his immediate family are restricted from scholarly access. Some records are restricted because they contain private medical information or to safeguard personal privacy.
  RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
  Scope and Contents note
  Record Group 2 of the Laurance S. Rockefeller Papers contains LSR's personal files from the Office of the Messieurs Rockefeller (OMR), for the period from mainly 1920 up to 1961 (21 cubic feet). The OMR Files form six series: Correspondence (Family and General), Personal Papers, Business Interests, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, Financial Materials, and LSR Family. The note for each of these series describes its contents and particular strengths.
  The Office of the Messieurs Rockefeller was the name given the Rockefeller family office in the period following the Second World War, when John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s sons returned from service to assume an increasing role in family business and philanthropic endeavors, even as they were pursuing their own careers and interests. The office provided family members with a range of services from routine office support (office space, staffing, purchasing, payroll and accounting, travel, security) to specialized investment and philanthropic advising, legal counsel, and a public relations staff. To support their broad activity – a 1951 list of the family's associations detailed more than seventy organizations in which the five Rockefeller brothers actively participated in a business or philanthropic capacity – the family had long relied on a system of associates who worked with individual family members and provided specialized assistance and advice. The Rockefeller family office was originally located at 26 Broadway in the Standard Oil Building, but it moved to Rockefeller Center when the RCA Building opened in the fall of 1933. The family office occupied the 56th floor (and eventually the 54th and 55th floors) of the RCA Building, and was known as Room 5600. Rockefeller philanthropies such as the American Conservation Association or the Rockefeller Brothers Fund also operated out of the family office space, and many affiliated businesses (such as Eastern Air Lines and eventually Rockresorts, Inc.) were neighboring Rockefeller Center tenants.
  LSR's OMR Files originally formed a separate series in the broader records of the Rockefeller family office under John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his children. The general OMR files document the broad range of the family's business and philanthropic interests. Files are grouped by subject area, and records documenting activities in a particular area of interest are generally found within the subject series. The LSR OMR files contain materials relating personally to LSR, but in many cases they provide only a skeletal or accidental record of his activities and involvements during this period. One must consult the general OMR files, under Business Interests or Cultural Interests, for example, to fill in details of LSR's involvement in the aviation business, or his work to create the Jackson Hole Wildlife Park, or any number of other activities.
  Similarly, the folder titles in the OMR Files record group imply a more comprehensive documentation of LSR's personal life than they provide. While the OMR files touch on LSR's youth, education, marriage, and naval service, these aspects of his life are more fully documented in a separate group of personal papers (Record Group 1) that was never part of the family office records.
  - Correspondence, 1919-1962, 1964; 1; 6 box(es)
    The Correspondence files are arranged in a chronological order, followed by a series of alphabetical folders. The family office grouped exchanges of correspondence with an individual or around an issue and filed the letters together by date of the latest item, forming small subject or personal categories within the chronological files. When LSR's correspondence with an individual was significant or sustained, we have brought the correspondence together and created a series of individual alphabetical files. The alphabetical listing reflects the volume and distribution of the correspondence more than the prominence of the correspondent. Also, a few individual files (for Rhoda French, Robert Lodge, Randolph Marston, and Leonard Outhwaite) have been moved from Personal Papers to the Correspondence series, and in some cases additional correspondence has been integrated into the files.
    LSR's correspondence files are divided into general and family correspondence, containing both incoming and outgoing correspondence. Replies are generally filed with the correspondence.
    The general Correspondence files contain personal correspondence with friends and relations, as well as some correspondence with associates concerning activities and organizations with which LSR was involved. The bulk of the correspondence dates from around 1935 to 1961; earlier materials in the files, dating from 1919, are about LSR (for example, concerning schooling or camp), rather than being direct correspondence with him. There are some gaps in the correspondence during LSR's college years and during the period of his military service from 1942-1945. (This correspondence is found in a separate personal papers series that never formed part of the OMR files.)
    Significant correspondents include Lincoln School and Princeton friends; friends and associates from LSR's service with the U.S. Navy Bureau of Aeronautics, Eastern Airlines, the New York City Airport Authority, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, and other organizations; cousins and in-laws (Margaret Strong de Cuevas, Madeline Prentice, the French family); and family friends and business associates. LSR's prominence as a Rockefeller and as an innovative investor accounts for some correspondence from acquaintances who wrote with product ideas or seeking references or other support.
    Also in the Correspondence files is a Mail Log of incoming correspondence, which LSR's office maintained starting in 1953. There are two bound ledgers for the period 1953 to July 1961 and one folder for June-December 1961, which record mail received and its disposition. (See RG 3 for the continuation of this series from 1962-1983 and 1986.)
    The Family Correspondence files contain LSR's correspondence with his parents and siblings and with his aunt, Lucy Truman Aldrich. Letters are filed chronologically by correspondent. There is a calendar to the Family Correspondence, which was created by family archivist Joseph W. Ernst. Some family correspondence was moved from the general correspondence files to the respective family folder. Letters from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. prior to 1933 in particular were originally filed with the general correspondence. The file of letters from Abby Aldrich Rockefeller for the period 1920-1933 contains mainly typed copies.
    A set of original letters and telegrams to LSR from his parents Abby Aldrich Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1920-1933, was discovered after the OMR files were processed. We have added this correspondence to the collection, but have not attempted to match up the letters or integrate them into the other correspondence files for AAR and JDR Jr. (This set of correspondence was found among the papers of LSR's associate, Fred Smith, who was preparing a biography of LSR; it appears the correspondence was lent to him for copying.) The correspondence includes many of the letters for which there are only typescripts in the original files, and it also includes some letters that are not otherwise represented in the collection.
    LSR's early letters to his family and some correspondence with his siblings during his college years are not found among the OMR files. Similarly, there is no correspondence in this series with his wife, Mary French Rockefeller.
    - General, 1919-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes a photostat of a Non-Smoking Pledge signed by the eighth-grade class of the Lincoln School, December 3, 1923.
    - General, 1928-1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General, 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - General, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - General, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - General, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - General, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - General, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - General, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - General, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14 A)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Restricted material.
    - General, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - General, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 15 A)
    - General, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - General, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - General, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 17 A)
      Restricted - Confidential material.
    - General, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - General, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - General, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 19 A)
    - General, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - General, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 20 A)
    - General, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - General, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 21 A)
    - General, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      General note
      Includes S. Benedict on ""Women in American Life"
    - General, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 22 A)
    - General, 1961 January-October (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - General, 1961 January-October (Box 2, Folder 23 A)
    - General, 1961 December -1962, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      1964 memo on JDR, Jr. Office furnishings
    - General, Undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Letter from D.A. [Elizabeth F. Billings] to LSR
    - General - Albertson, Atta, 1929-1934 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      Alphabetical
    - General - Armstrong, Thomas R., 1938-1957 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - General - Callahan, Roy, 1946-1961 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - General - Canaday - Chorley, 1955-1961 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      Alphabetical. Canaday, Ward M., 1955-1961; Chorley, Kenneth, and Jean T., 1960-1961
    - General - Clarke, Karl L., 1943-1956; Still Images: 9 black-and-white glossy prints (4" x 5"). (Box 3, Folder 30)
      Includes snapshots of Independence Day ceremony, Republic of the Philippines, [July 4, 1946], enclosed in Karl Clarke to LSR, August 11, [1946]. Photos stamped "Counter Intelligence Corps Photograph."
    - General - Clarke, Karl L. (oversized file), 1948 (Box 53, Folder 702)
      2 line drawings of Friendship International Airport, Baltimore, MD, Terminal Building floor plans.
    - General - Coleman - Compston, 1950-1961 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Alphabetical. Coleman, John, 1950-1956; Compston, Archie, 1951-1961
    - General - Cuevas, George and Margaret Strong de, 1933-[1934] (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - General - D (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Alphabetical. Davis, Vietor, 1945; Debenham, Frank, 1932-1942; Drake, Francis V., 1952-1959 (includes postcard of Zurich-Kloten Airport); Duncan, William, 1945-1961.
    - General - Firestone, 1946-1961 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Alphabetical. Firestone, Leonard, 1946-1960; Firestone, Roger, 1946-1961
    - General - French, Mary Billings, 1935-1949 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - General - French, Rhoda, 1947-1955 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - General - H (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Alphabetical. Hitchcock, Elizabeth French, 1937-1938; Hitchcock, Ethan A., 1945-1960; Hooker, Donald H., 1947-1957
    - General - Johnson - Lewis, 1940-1961 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Alphabetical. Johnson, Robert W., 1940-1961; Lewis, Daniel H., 1943-1959
    - General - Lodge, Robert, 1951-1964 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Personal loans from LSR. Virgin Islands Nurseries (orchids); Emerald Bay project; East End Development Corp., St. Croix
    - General - Lord - McClave, 1940-1954 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      Alphabetical. Lord, Jere and June Harrah, 1942-1954; McClave, William, 1940-1946
    - General - Marston, Randolph, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 41)